Guide to the Records of the Office of the Registrar RG.12.4
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Registrar
1832-2017
1832-1968
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of the Registrar
Tompkins, Leslie J. (Leslie Jay), 1867-1952
Stevenson, John J. (John James), 1841-1924
Ladue, Pomeroy
New York College of Music
RG.12.4
9.32 Linear Feet in 18 custom boxes, 1 manuscript box, 3 oversize flat boxes, and 3 folders in shared housing
The Office of the Registrar is responsible for the integrity of academic policies, the student information system and student records from application to degree conferral. The office works to protect and preserve the academic records of New York University's students and to provide a framework for students to navigate the academic process. The Records of the Office of the Registrar consist of materials created and collected by the Office documenting student records and degree requirements. The majority of the collection consists of handwritten ledgers dating between 1832 and 1916. The collection also includes administrative memoranda and correspondence, ledgers and lists of enrolled students, sample diplomas and certificates, programs (including commencement programs), and materials documenting student military service. Some materials were created by employees of the New York College of Music, which merged with NYU in the middle of the 20th century.
Scope and Contents
The Records of the Office of the Registrar consist of materials created and collected by the Office documenting student records and degree requirements. The majority of the collection consists of handwritten ledgers dating between 1832 and 1916. The majority of the ledgers track applications for admission, student matriculation, class rolls, grades, and citations for meritorious conduct. A scrapbook compiled by the college's first registrar, Leslie J. Tompkins, documents the construction of and repairs to several buildings on the Heights Campus; endowments, scholarships, and prizes granted to students; commencement and lecture programs; and annual reports from the Treasurer's and the Registrar's offices. One volume lists officers and platoons, possibly in an early campus security organization; roll calls and lists of officers sent on patrol; and entries documenting arrests. One volume consists of a letterbook, containing letters written by J. J. Stevenson as registrar and Pomeroy Ladue as secretary regarding admission, coursework, and commencement in the graduate school in the 1890s. The collection also includes administrative memoranda and correspondence, ledgers and lists of enrolled students, sample diplomas and certificates, programs (including commencement programs), and materials documenting student military service. Some materials were created by employees of the New York College of Music, which merged with NYU in the middle of the 20th century.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
There is no documentation concerning the provenance of the ledgers housed in Boxes 1-18. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 90.020 and 2019.113. In January 2025, Tyrell Davis, Associate Registrar, transferred additional materials including correspondence, ledgers and lists, event programs, and sample diplomas and certificates. The accession number associated with this transfer is 2025.008.
Historical Note
The Office of the Registrar is responsible for the integrity of academic policies, the student information system and student records from application to degree conferral. The office works to protect and preserve the academic records of New York University's students and to provide a framework for students to navigate the academic process.
Appraisal
35mm slides of images of the NYU campus taken by the Photo Bureau and graduation programs already in the Archives' holdings were appraised out of this accretion prior to acquisition.
Ledgers (account books); Universities and Colleges -- Admission.; Education, Higher -- New York (N.Y.)
- Matriculation Book, 1832-1843; cuid18097 (Box 1)
- Matriculation Book, 1853-1893; cuid18098 (Box 2)
- Matriculation Book, 1894-1909; cuid18099 (Box 2)
- Class Merit Book, 1835-1888 (Box 3)
- Records of Grades, Department of Arts and Science, 1884-1894 (Box 15)
- Record Book, University College, 1886-1894 (Box 4)
- Record Book, University College, 1895-1897 (Box 5)
- Records of Grades, University College, 1890-1902 (Box 6)
- Records of Grades, School of Applied Science, Volume I, 1900-1909 (Box 7)
- Records of Grades, University College, 1900-1909 (Box 8)
- Records of Grades, School of Applied Science, Volume II, 1907-1909 (Box 9)
- Records of Actions on Applications for Admission, 1896-1900 (Box 12)
- Registrar's File, 1896-1904 (Box 11)
- Letterbook of Registrar of the Graduate School, 1890-1897 (Box 13)
- Attendance books, 1881-1891 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
- List of Students with Addresses and Activities, 1895-1903 (Box 16)
- Columbian Exposition Register of signatures of members of the University of the City of New York, 1893 (Box 17)
- Student rolls from University College and School of Applied Science, 1905-1916 (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
- New York University Ledger, 1870-1871 (Box 18)
- Faculty of Applied Science Students on Probation, 1908-1909 (Box 10)
- Certificates Issued to Students Upon Completion of Courses in Meteorology, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Commencement Programs, 1914-1915 (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Commencement Program, 1917 (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Commencement Programs, 1918-1919 (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Junior Year in Spain Certificates, 1960 (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Letters to Recent Graduates, 2017 (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Military Service, 1942-1943 (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Sample Diplomas and Certificates -- General, 1924-1962 (Box 19, Folder 8, Box 22, Folder 1-10, Box Shared University Archives 152, Folder 14-16)
- Sample Diplomas and Certificates -- Specific Schools, undated (Box 20, Folder 1-5, Box 21)
- Selective Service System, 1956-1969 (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Student Record Ledger: Testimonial Certificate, Diploma, and Other Degrees (New York College of Music), 1905-1934 (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Student Record Ledger: Testimonial Certificate, Diploma, and Other Degrees (New York College of Music), 1935-1968 (Box 19, Folder 11)
- University Heights Commencement Program, 1931 (Box 19, Folder 12)
- Visiting Committee Certificates (Discontinued), 1952 (Box 19, Folder 13)
- Wall Street, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 14)